I think it's pretty well established
across the health sphere that insulin
resistance leading to eventual diabetes
is a major contributor to heart disease.
But there are a lot of unanswered
questions because while it's often
assumed that the risk comes from high
blood sugar, could it also be due to
sugar's shadow insulin? And if insulin
is a factor in heart disease, is it
always an issue if it's present or is it
only an issue in particular contexts?
Well, I wanted to find out because it
was a point of discussion between Dr.
Peter Aia and a diabetes researcher, Dr.
Ralph Defrrono in a lengthy podcast on
the topic of insulin resistance. So,
we'll listen in, but we'll also bring in
some studies to identify what is what is
all insulin aogenic, meaning artery
plaque promoting. As you pointed out,
rightfully so. You know, I believe that
high levels of insulin are also aogenic.
Now, I don't want people saying, "Dr.
Def Franzo said you shouldn't be giving
insulin to people who need it." Of
course, uh if people need insulin, you
need to give them insulin. But our beta
cells make 35 units of insulin per day.
If you're a type 1 diabetic, and again,
Sure. What What do you mean? So, you
during the You're going to have your
breakfast, you're going to have your
lunch, you're going to have your dinner.
And if I were to add, I'm sorry, 35
units. I thought you meant micro units.
Got it. Yeah.
35 units of insulin. So we showed this
many years ago when I actually was at
Yale that if you were to take a type one
patient and they were lean, they would
only need 35 or 40 units of insulin to
get their uh glucose controlled,
assuming you gave the doses at the right
time. But we have a lot of people who
are taking 100 units of insulin, both
type ones and type twos. So 3x
physiologic. Yes, that kind of
hyperinsulinemia. I think there's
evidence to support that's agogenic. So,
Dr. Defranzo is of the mind that high
insulin is aogenic. Again, increasing
plaque formation in the arteries. And
yet, that creates a bit of an issue,
right? Considering type 1 diabetics and
in later stages, type 2 diabetics are
literally injecting insulin into
themselves. Are they injecting the very
substance that will kill them? Well, Dr.
Dr. Ia describes the conundrum. But now
we have a problem. Okay. Can you have
the glucose remain high? Yeah. It's a
question of do you want to die quickly
or or or slowly because we have really
good drugs. Yes. Yes. Yes. But if if you
were only doing this with insulin be a
problem. It's an awful trade-off. It's
you're going to die very quickly from
hyperglycemia if you're left untreated.
But if we overdo it with insulin to
maintain normal glycemia, we're going to
kill you slowly. It's a quagma. You're
stuck. Y you have to treat. But you also
know that when you're giving these big
doses of insulin, there may be some side
effects. In the case of severe insulin
resistance, not type 1 diabetes, it's
true that a person can then avoid the
insulin and die quickly because glucose,
blood sugar, is no longer entering the
cells, which means that the cells lose
functionality or die from a lack of
nutrients feeding them. or the glucose
glycates sticks and inhibits the many
functional components of the cell
rendering the cell less functional or a
person can inject insulin and in this
case two to three times the normal
amount of insulin which as we'll discuss
reres havoc on the body. It's really a
pretty big quagmire. This is something
Ralph I don't think that has been
necessarily appreciated by the medical
community has it? Oh absolutely not.
Yeah, that there has generally been an
ethos of when I've talked to patients
with type two diabetes um that what
they've been told is I'm told to cover
with as much insulin as is necessary to
maintain my glucose levels uh in this
range and it means I can eat whatever I
want. It's okay if I have all the pasta
and bread and sugar in the world because
as long as I'm covering it with insulin,
I'm okay. And then you find out, wow,
you're taking 150 units of insulin a day
in all of its forms, the short acting,
the long acting, etc. But but I didn't
actually realize that that what we would
consider physiologic is 35. I I may have
known that at one point and I've since
forgotten, but that's a great reference.
So basically, if there's a person with
type 2 diabetes listening to us today
and they're taking 75 units of insulin,
the one of the takeaways should be what
do I need to do with my nutrition and
other pharmacologic activities plus
exercise plus everything that's under my
control to maybe get that down to 35
where I would be at a physiologic level.
Right? So, if a physician is focusing on
only one half of the equation, the blood
glucose, and not focusing on the insulin
needed to get the blood glucose into the
acceptable ranges, they're simply
changing the poison, or at least that's
the idea. But does it stack up to the
scientific literature? Well, I did find
a scientific review that discusses
insulin resistance, including
hyperinsulinemia, that's elevated
insulin, and the effect on plaque
formation in the arteries. Now,
unfortunately, the majority of the
review focuses on insulin resistance,
which is important, but doesn't answer
our question about insulin itself.
However, it does offer a few clues like
in this study. So to orient you, the
researchers applied insulin at low and
extremely high doses to smooth muscle
cells. These cells are located here in
the artery. They're responsible for
direct blood pressure control and they
also migrate out of their resting place
in the subendothelium in advancing forms
of plaque formation to sit on top of the
plaque. Okay. Insulin directly to the
cells. that's independent of insulin
resistance, blood glucose, and so on.
However, the researchers also
genetically manipulated some of the
smooth muscle cells to have massively
diminished ability to produce the
insulin receptor that sits in the cell
membrane. So, one condition has normal
cells and the other is the same cells
with a deficient insulin signaling, but
they're both exposed to insulin. Here
are the results. You can ignore the top
unless you're a molecular biologist.
Then well, have at it. For 99% of you,
focus on the graph. We have added
insulin increasing concentration on the
horizontal axis. And we're measuring AKT
activation. What is that? AKT is a
famous protein. So famous that I got a
selfie with it. Don't be too envious
though. Anyway, it's a famous protein
because it's heavily involved in insulin
signaling. So if the lines go up, that
means that there's more signaling
through AKT. The wild type condition
there are the normal cells and the L2
are the insulin receptor deficient
cells. For those with a molecular
biology degree, I'd call it a massive
reduction, but not a complete knockout.
Anyway, we see that uh AKT is more
strongly activated in the normal cells
and might even increase with greater
insulin exposure. This makes some sense
since the L2 cells shouldn't be able to
activate AKT. And yet, when we look at a
cell signal that is tightly related to
inflammation and cell migration, the
script is flipped. The insulin receptor
deficient cells have higher activation
of a protein heavily implicated in
atherosclerosis progression. H why might
that be? Well, the researchers do show
there's a greater cell migration like
that might be seen in atherosclerosis
with the smooth muscle cells. But if the
insulin receptor is greatly diminished,
how is the cell reacting to this
insulin? We'll get into that, but we
need to discuss another study first, one
that gets much closer to dividing the
topic of insulin resistance and exposure
to insulin as a whole. I promise I'll
tie into what we just went over. I'll
explain that later. This other study has
been heavily referenced in the initial
review. It's this one. I have to admit,
I think this study is really clever. The
researchers are manipulating simple
physiology to uncover the real effect of
insulin alone, but they aren't adding
insulin like in the last study. They're
letting the body raise blood insulin
levels without killing the subject.
Okay, what am I alluding to? The
researchers are using genetically
manipulated mice and they're using these
mice for good reason. They're using APOE
deficient mice, which means that these
mice form plaque fil arteries at a much
faster rate than normal. It allows the
researchers to detect an effect in a
much shorter amount of time. But that's
not the only clever part. They also
genetically manipulated one group of
mice to be insulin receptor haplo
insufficient. Meaning only one of their
insulin genes is able to produce
functional insulin receptor. You see
what this means? It means that these
mice will have greater blood insulin
levels around 50% more in their blood
and that insulin will bind fewer insulin
receptors keeping the mice from dying
from too low of blood sugar yet still
have the necessary hyperinsulinemia so
elevated insulin. This effectively
separates the insulin resistance from
the insulin itself which is a really
beautiful design. In addition, the mice
were perfectly insulin sensitive. Again,
marvelous design. So, what happened? Did
they develop plaque in their arteries at
a faster rate? Well, look for yourself.
The images are images of arteries
excised from the mice. The left is the
normal mice and the delta there is the
haplo insufficient mice. The red is
plaque and the graphs on the bottom are
the average results across multiple
mice.
There's no difference. These data
indicate that high insulin alone does
not have an effect on atherosclerosis
and likely a person has to be insulin
resistant to experience the detrimental
effects of insulin on atherosclerosis.
There's more to say on that to add
context that we'll get to, but I'd like
to return to the first primary study
that we just went over and why cell
migration was greater in cells with this
massively reduced insulin
receptor. You would think there would be
no effect, but it turns out that there
is an effect that as we saw. So why?
Actually, before we get to that, did you
know that I have an even more
science-packed version of this video
that you're watching? You either
screamed in horror or got very excited.
If you're in the latter camp, it's true.
I cover much more on these mechanisms of
insulin and insulin resistance,
including some more of what Dr. Defranzo
mentions, which is even counterintuitive
to what we discussed, at least
initially. If you're interested, check
out the full analysis video included
with the Physionic Insiders. And if you
really want to nerd out, join me in my
live sessions where I dive even deeper
into these topics and we can discuss and
nerd out together. Also included with
the insider membership. Anyway, the link
is in the description. I'll hope to see
you there. Before I rudely interrupted
with an advertisement for the Physionic
Insiders, I asked why is there an effect
of cell migration, a component of
atherosclerosis in smooth muscle cells
that are greatly reduced in their
insulin receptor levels? Well, according
to the researchers, it's believed,
although research is ongoing, that in
insulin resistance, cells will often
reduce the expression of their insulin
receptors, much like the artificially
created in the study. However, another
receptor becomes more prominent. That
receptor is called the insulin-like
growth factor receptor or IGF-1
receptor. Now, there's a bit of
complexity in this that I'm going to
keep for the extended version because
it's just too much to cover here. But
insulin can also bind this IGF-1
receptor and it will preferentially
activate the ERK pathway or the IRK
pathway that we discussed earlier as
well as instigate cell migration. We're
making some assumptions here because we
don't fully have the data to back that
claim. So don't consider this foolproof,
but it would explain one mechanism as to
why insulin resistance in combination
with insulin leads to increased
atherosclerosis. So plaque progression
while insulin alone does not. Anyway,
where does that land us on the question
of insulin and being agogenic, plaque
promoting? Well, I don't think this is
enough evidence to completely absolve
insulin, but it at least begins to offer
us evidence that the insulin molecule
isn't inherently harmful. The context
likely matters more than the molecule
itself. So, no, the injections of
physiological insulin used in type 1
diabetics is unlikely to enhance plaque
formation. But increasing doses used in
later stages of type 2 diabetes and even
pancreatic production with pre-diabetes
are more than likely contributing to
plaque formation since context is
longstanding insulin resistance. That
can be fixed though a variety of ways
from exercising which is incredibly
powerful in blood glucose and insulin
management but also nutrition, weight
loss, low carb diets, plant-based diets,
and everything in between that focuses
away from processed hyperc caloric foods
can have a tremendous effect. Or Dr.
Defranzo mentions a triple therapy
that's cheap and powerful that he uses
with people with severe insulin
resistance. I cover that all in this
follow-up here. See you over there.
[Music]